hey guys welcome to concept and coding
and this is Shan and today we are going
to do this JWT Json WB token and if you
have not seen the O and cryptography
videos in the same playlist then I would
highly recommend to go through this
because JWT is highly linked with it o
uses JWT and JWT uses cryptographic keys
and all right so go through that on it's
already been covered and today let's
just start without any wasting time what
is
JWT so in a very very simple
term it provides a secure way of
transmitting information between parties
as a Json
object right so you already know Json
object
right it would it's like key value pair
key and then value comma key value
objects generally right
so what JWT is just a secure way of
transmitting information between
parties okay this information can be
verified because it's digit digitally
sign using RS Etc like hm is one more
algo which we can use okay so the
message which you are transmitting
between parties that can be digitally
signed and how you can digitally signed
I have already explained in the
cryptography but for now in this
definition what you have to focus on is
it was developed as just a way of
transmitting information securely that's
all but over the time we are using JWT
in many different areas for
authentication for authorization and in
SSO when whenever you are doing single
sign on right you are using JWT and this
is also one of the good interview
question how you will Implement single
sign on to implement a single sign on
you need
JWT right so when I say that
authentication JWT is used for
authentication means confirming the user
identity if I am Shan it verifies that
yes he is Shan the message which is
coming from Shan authorization means
it's check for permission if I am trying
to fetch certain details then JWT also
helps in authorization that does Shan
has authority to fet this detail or not
yes authentication is done I am Shan but
do I have an authority to fetch certain
details or not that also you can do and
single sign on you already know that you
have signed in one application one you
have signed in you have already logged
in now there are different app app 2 app
3 right same
user so here you have signed in but with
a single sign on you can log to
different application now without trying
to provide your username password so it
it was built as a way of just
transmitting information securely but
this is today at this three places it is
highly
used and this advantages we will come
again once we have finished all the
understanding of the JWT because then
only it will make sense because when I
say that it is self-contained it's only
when you understand what is JWT how it
is a structure looks like then only you
will get to know yes it's self-contain
okay so don't worry we will come back to
its
Advantage one more time once we will
complet the JWT but for
now what is JWT and where today they are
highly used that should be in uh total
Clarity okay so this is you can say
a flow of JWT today in the
authentication uh part so this is let's
say this is a
client okay so this is the first happen
is so this is your author authentication
server so let's say any
server
which uh there are many third party
libraries available which provides you
the apis through which you can generate
token validate token and all right so
that's why any application authoriz
authentication
server so this is your app this is your
application
right so and this is let's say any third
party
application
which
support token
generation and validation okay there are
so many available today and that's one
of the advantages of JW that you don't
have to incorporate the authentication
logic in your yourself there are already
uh third party libraries available which
we can use and they will take care of
generating a token validating the token
for you you just have to invoke them
okay so let's call that third party
application as authentication server so
as a
client right first I have to provide the
username password so it will goes to an
authentication server you provided your
username password now what this
authentication server will do it will
generate the token and return right it
will generate the token JWT and it will
return back to the
client now client will do is the client
has the JWT now it wanted to access a
particular resource right so what it
will do is it will call our application
resource where the resource is actually
stored so it will call the resource and
pass the JWT in the header in the
header okay so let's say call the get
API this is the get API let's say uh
some details but it passed the JWT also
now what this resource server your
application will do is it will
internally calls the API of
authorization server let's say some
verify API and it will pass the token
which it get from the client now this
all this logic present in to
authentication server where it will
validate yes this token is generated by
me it is valid I'll tell you we will go
more deeper into the token part how it
validates it but just for now understand
that author uh authentication server
will validate the token and it will tell
to your application that yes this is
token is
verified it's valid it's valid token
once it is valid token resource owner
will grant you the permission and it
will turn you the
data okay so this is the flow diagram of
JWT so till now we are clear but before
we uh proceed further we need to
understand what was popular before
JWT and what are the problems with
it so if you remember right before JWT
there was something called session ID or
many engineers might know it through J
session ID I have worked with J session
ID right so but this was very very
popular session
ID so in this what used to happen is
let's say a client first what it will do
is it login with username password the
same let's say author authorization or
authentication server third party server
is there or generally what used to
happen was resource server itself
performs this task also generally there
is no third party library but for
simplification purpose let's say that
you have another
application
which generate the session ID okay so
first user provide a login with username
password it goes to your application
what it will do is it will create the
session ID and save it in
DB that's the important part it will put
into the DB that this is the session
ID right and store all the information
like expiry time let's say session ID
this belongs to this user this is the
expiry time and other information that
what are the
roles like it can only uh fetch user
details let's say certain roles it has
put so all this
data will put will be inserted into DB
and this ID session ID which is just a
unique random key will be given back to
the
client now with this ID so whenever it
send a request in the cookies this
client will also pass
this J session
ID right now this resource server has to
call the DB now with this J session ID
fetch all the details do all the logic
okay expiry time does it
expired roles these are the roles so
whatever the operation it wanted me to
do send like fetch this does it has this
roles or not so it will do lot of
validation at their side and if it is
got validated then only it it will send
the response else it will throw
error so one of the major major
catch is
that every time you are hitting a
request to F the
details it is hitting the DB to face the
details from this particular J session
ID why because at the time of creation
of J session ID when the time you
provided username password
it was stored in DB so it is State
full and JWT
is stat less there is no DB touch
whatever the JWT token we are returning
that JWT token has all the information
like expiry regarding user information
Etc so there is no need for d
B and that's one of the advantage that
it is
stateless
so your J session ID
is
stateful it rely on server side Estate
Management right and since DB comes into
the picture now you know that in case of
distributed system this might cause a
problem right let's say the server the
application which creates this session
ID into this DB right so there are let's
say different cluster of DB this is
Master Slave this is one cluster one
let's say there are different cluster of
DB so in a distributed system this all
has to be sync up all DBS has to be sync
up we don't know this get request this
get request comes to
where okay so in case of distributed
system extra handling need to be taken
care right and also one important part
is during your get
request your application has to query
the DB perform validation on top of it
so there would be an extra latency add
up of quiring the DB now let's go back
to the JWT again that what is it
structure how does it become stateless
right it needed so many information that
roles expiry user ID and maybe some
other unique ID how it is able to store
this just a
token right so this is the JWT structure
so there are three things right
JWT
jws jwe e but whenever we are talking
about JWT right ultimately actually we
are always talking
jws right so this you can say that
always used together JWT jws we will
I'll tell you how so let's say
understand this JWT structure JWT
structure has three part one after that
there is
a DOT period then this is the second
part then again there is a DOT and this
is the third part
okay so this first part is known as
header the second part is known as
payload and the third part is known as
signature right let's go one by one
header so header already contains the
metadata information of the token metad
data like what is the type always JWT
you will always find I have never seen
any other value apart from JWT till now
it's always
JWT elgo the signing algorithm so here
is the signing algorithm which you have
used RSA or
hmac right or if there are other
different algorithms you can use it
right RSA have already explained you in
the previous cryptographic video and
hmac is also I've explained you this is
uh
symmetric this is symmetric cryptography
key this is a symmetric cryptography key
right so I've already explained this so
header contains information about
metadata of the payload and the
signature now your payload so I told you
that payload actually contains the
information or you can say that actually
contain
claims right so in simple terms user
information or any additional
information is kept here right JWT see
that these are the
claims the understand claims nothing
like a just an information whatever you
want to cap so this claims are divided
into three parts registered claims
public
claims private claims okay so in the
payload it is all comes under this only
all comes under this
only but let's say that there are
certain this
Words which are reserved by JWT so those
are known as registered claims
they have very specific meaning for
example
ISS which JWT understand as
issuer the entity that issued the JWT
for example ISS is issued by some uh JWT
issuer at
theate something some website link or
something which identifies who is the
issuer then subject identifies the user
let's say subject sub 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 some
unique identifier which identifies the
user who is the
user then your audience identify the
recipient for which token is intended
AUD let's say AUD would be uh your
whatever your your company name or
anything for which it identify the
recipient then expiry time after this so
exp is is like which tell the expiry
time after this time token is not
valid then NBF not before time before
this token should not be
accepted right so whatever the time is
there before that you cannot accept the
token and expiry is that after that this
token is not
valid then there is something called IAT
the time which token is issued and jti
is unique J ID some unique ID for this
token so if you see that these names are
reserved by JWT means they have pre uh
predefined name and
meaning but now let's say that apart
from this registered name you have to
put some other like I have put here
email though those would be considered
as a public claim it's a custom claim
which can be shared and understood by
multiple parties right so I have given
the name email anybody can understand
that it will contain an email ID of the
user right or
certains don't never ever put some very
very you can say that confidential
information inside a
payload like some password or all never
put never put your confidential
information inside a payload right so
let's say email apart from that let's
say that uh okay um some C uh country so
I can put country let's say
India so if you see that these are not
registered names I can put anything
email country City or let's say that
last name first name so these are you
can say that a public claim which is
understood which is understood by
multiple parties right they know that
okay country I will get the what is the
country name for this user like City I
know that this what city belongs
to so these are the public claims these
are custom claims you can use any but it
should be shared and understood by
multiple
parties then there is something called
private claims which is like understood
by
this your authentication server itself
so let's say that it calls that username
password
now this authentication server has to
generate the token now let's say it has
put uh
I some IM
am right and this is uh let's say
resource server and resource server one
resource server 2 and it is passing this
token to this JWT token to
this now does resource server one
understood this what is am what is am it
hasn't understood it even though it is
present inside here in the payload let's
say another I
am this is not understood by resource
server one resource server two when they
pass it to authorization server for
validate only this understood it maybe
for some internal purpose it might have
added it which is not understood by
multiple parties that's what known as
private claim public claim is under by
multiple parties like let's say country
yes now resource server can understood
that this is the country for the user
but what is imem I don't know I don't
know only authentication server might
know it who has added it so that is
known as private claim it is again a
custom claim you can add anything but
these are not identified for but these
are intended for internal use only and
not
standardized right so these are not
standard like not expected other parties
to know this resource server one doesn't
know this resource server two doesn't
know this authentication server which
created it they only noce it that's why
known as private
claim so understood so in the payload
you can have have this claims but these
claims are generally divided into three
parts but it all under the same objects
just an
object now the third part is your
signature this is very very important
and that's why I told you sometime JWT
and jws when we whoever tells you JWT
sometimes also covers jws because
signature the third part of uh token is
your signature and that's what jws also
is Json WAP signature okay so they are
used you can say that
interchangeably so now what signature
now you now you have
header now you have
payload now what you will do how you
will get a
signature so what signature will do is
it will first encode JWT header it will
first
encode header base
64 encoder it will do
header payload also it will do uh encode
basic 64 encoding for this payload so it
will also
do base
64 encoding for
payload so it first encoded this header
and it then it first encoded this
payload
okay then in con and concatenate the
header and payload using this dot period
so it will put a period and then it
concact inate this so it's now one
string
okay so it would become like this your
header and then your encoded payload
encoded header encoded payload so this
is known as your
message or generally you can say that uh
your
information now you are using RSC or any
cryptographic either a symmetric or
symmetric to create a digital signature
now you will pass it this message string
to
algorithm right so this is your one
string
message comma some key because now we
are passing it to algorithm if you are
using RSA for example a symmetric key
you have to pass here private
key if you are using hmac you have to
pass one secret key and the same secret
key would be used at the time
of digitally
signing it digitally verifying
it right because in symmetric key the
same key is used same key is used while
signing and while verifying it while
right and in the RSA two keys are used
uh private key and public key so during
signing it is signed through private key
and during verifying the signature it is
verified through public
key
okay now once you have uh got this
signature let's say some
string encode the signature also
generate in the previous step you can
encode it right now let's say you have
so whatever the signature you got let's
say x y z a b c this is the signature
you
got right you have to encode it also
you have to encode it base 64 encode it
also and concatenate using this dot so
your
header base 64 your header
dot base 64 your
payload dot now your base 64 encode of
your
signature got it so ultimately this is
your JWT going to looks like so this is
your P 64 of
header
dot this is your base 64 encoding of
your
payload dot this is your base 64 en code
of your signature
value and how the signature value is
generated I told you okay so here I have
shown one sample uh get
request here I have shown you one sample
API here if you see that I am making a
get request to this some dummy
API okay and in the header part there is
a header called authorization you have
to pass like beer and pass this this
token now you can ask me right why we
have to pass this beer so in the header
right there are you can add multiple
like key
value right so one of the standard
industry standard is that wherever you
are passing the credential you have to
pass the credential into authorization
header so that it would be handled
accordingly by the server right so
that's why I told you right there are
certain industry standard that yes I
will get credential so it should be
inside this header of the authorization
so they can put a specific logic it
should not be like randomly anywhere
coming
so this is the header name they have
decided that okay authorization put
inside this now inside this
authorization there are multiple thing
like
basic
beer when like you are doing that basic
and then some encoded value a b c d e f
g something so basic means that you are
passing
username password so when you decode
this base 64 value decode this for the
basic you will get like something that
this username colon
password but if you are passing like
beer and then value then server will
understand that okay this is not
username password this is token beer
means like industry standard means token
is passed to me so I should behave in
accordingly okay so you might have a
different logic if user name password
passed you might have a different logic
that okay if beer comes means token is
passed to me then I have to call certain
server and validate
it okay so JWT is always passed from
client to server in the header of
authorization but with the beerer word
not basic remember basic is for username
password so credentials always passed
into
authorization so this is the sample
request okay so now before going to the
challenges with
JWT
so now let's come back to Advantage
first thing is you understand that it's
a
compact we are encoding it and because
of its size it can be go inside a header
itself HTTP header itself and it
transmission is also fast because of its
small
size I have already told you it is
stateless it is self-contained all the
information you can Capt it expiry time
user ID
anything
it is can be digitally signed so I've
already told you jws generally what we
understand JWT so we are we are adding a
signature right so that is jws so means
we are signing your token so JWT jws is
using interchangeably you can say that
so we can sign it using hm and RSA and
when you sign it at the receiver end you
can validate that yes the message is not
changed at
all right built in expiry time I told
you that it is stateless you can add
expiry uh time here so you don't need DB
so built-in expir expiry mechanism is
there custom claim additional data can
be added in JWT like roles you have to
add certain roles for this user you can
add it into the claim itself so these
are all the advantage of JWT which makes
it
stateless but now very very important
part from interview perceptive what are
the challenges with JWT so you
understood till now right but before
challenges I will also tell you that uh
let's say single sign on
SSO so let's say that this is your
company you have app
one app
2 app three this is you so now I think
you already know what how the single
sign on works so first it will goes to
certain authentication server where it
provided username password it will get
the JWT
token now what does happen with the
single sign on is let's say you are
trying to log in to uh you are trying to
opening this
F1 www. let's say f1.com you trying to
open it so what it will do is it will
pass the JWT token also whatever the you
have received and when this app1
received JWT token it internally try to
verifies the your JWT if it verifies it
will sign
in right and all this user information
like let's say username email ID is
already available in your payload so it
can help you to sign in say hi Shan how
does it know it knows to JWT token
itself that payload has may be my name
my email ID ID so it able to verify me
similarly when it able to goes to app2
it will pass the JWT app to uses the
let's say verify this token from the
server authentication server once it Val
validated
so verification signature everything is
all good nothing tampered it will help
me sign in also so here if you see only
once I have provided the username
password I got the token now the same
token I'm using it to login at multiple
places so that is known as SSO and this
is implemented through JWT now there is
one big problem with
JWT token
invalidation since JWT is
stateless what does stateless means that
these servers application Server doesn't
know about this JWT at
all right it is issued to a user now
once it comes to them they just validate
it if it is valid they will provide it
the
access now let's say that this user is
fraud user this is
fraud now I want to
block now I want to block him block this
user but this user has a token which has
expiry time of let's say
uh today is uh March let's say April
till 20th or uh 21st April so till 21st
April this has a valid token now even
though this is a fraud user how you will
make this token invalidate if I make
this request to this application to it
will check with the server pass this
token hey this token is valid it its
expiry is not yet come so how you will
invalidate the Tok token so let's say
that I have a blacklisted user how to
invalidate a token before its expiration
biggest
problem so there are today multiple ways
through which we are doing
this first is server need to keep the
list of blacklisted
tokens right and either the DB or cash
up lookup is required while validating
so
here you have authentication server
right and then there you have app one
app 2 multiple so it can maintain
a token blacklisted blacklisted tokens
right and each token is identified uning
a particular ID I already told you there
is something called J jti unique token
ID right so now let's say that based on
that it put the particular jti this
token is invalid this is
blacklisted now when uh this fraud user
is passing the JWT token and it is
trying to validate it it will check its
blacklisted whether it's putting it in
cash whether it
is putting it in DB this blacklisted
list it can validate that hey this token
ID is there in the blacklisted L I need
to deny
it but this has a problem that which the
problem earlier you were solving with
session ID avoid look up of DB or cash
now you are doing that okay so this is
one problem but so this this will solve
the problem but this again has a
disadvantage that you have to do a DB or
cash lookup okay what are the other ways
the another way is just change the
secret key
itself so the change the secret key uh
let's say that the uh earlier you were
using for signing it you are using RSA
let's say you are using private key
public key one this is public key one
now you have changed this key to 22 so
now at the time of
verification it will verify the
signature right so now it will try to
verify with the new public key so it
will invalidate because it was signed
through one private key one
and if it will only be verified properly
if you sign it with public key one only
but now you have changed the key itself
so it
will it will Deni the user but what is
the problem or if the apart from this
fraud user if there are some genuine
user
also which was given a token using
private key one which was given a token
which was signed using private key one
that will not be able to access access
your data also they might have to log in
again so that's the problem thatth
second is if you change the secret key
this will solve the problem but this
will make the JWT invalidate for all
genuine user also but this is you can
say that again a
problem what other thing we can do is
make a token should be very short live
instead of till
April right let's say instead of till
April what if I make that okay uh only
for 5 minutes your token is
valid only for 5 minutes your token is
valid okay so this will resolve a
problem but still till 5 minute that
problem exist so this sometimes is very
popular and also this is popular that
token should be used only
once so generally this is combined token
should be used only once plus very short
live let's say 5 minutes and it should
be used only
once after that you should generate a
new token so this might solve a
problem okay so but these are the
different ways based upon your
requirement uh one of the solution is
implemented right so can you can also
ask me that hey sh how do we know that
to token should be used only once again
to implement this this uh J J jti the
unique token ID jti unique token ID is
some somebody it has to be stored in
cash or somewhere where it will check
that hey I have seen this token
before right so somewhere it has to do
the DB so but you can say that the
shortlived tokens are that's why very
popular it's not whenever you get a
token it's not valid for One Day 2 Day
one month they are very
shli use it for in within 5 10 minutes
after that you have to might need to log
in
again okay so token invalidation has a
problem genuine problem there are
different solution for this based upon
the requirement of the let's say the
question which has been asked or your
company multiple uh you can say that mix
or one of the solution is
implemented second JWT token is encoded
not encrypted so it's less secure I told
you right you have
header then you have payload and then
you have signature part ultimately token
is your encoding of header dot encoding
of payload dot encoding Bas 64 encoding
of your signature value which ultimately
got so here if you see that payload has
mostly all the
information and that is encoded and you
know that this encoded payload you can
simply do base 64 decode and you will
get the data so this is less secure and
for that jwe comes into the picture
which is Json web
encryption so what it does is nothing
exactly same what we are doing but
instead of encoding this uh letter of
this payload it will do encryption of
this payload that's all and at the
receiver side when verify should be
happen they can decrypt it so your
authentication server knows the keys
let's say RSA for encryption decryption
encryption should happen through public
key decryption should happen through
private key we have already discussed in
the previous video right but JWT is
Right encrypt your payload
only so JWT token is encoded not
encrypted it's let secure what to do go
for jwe in the jwe your payload part is
encrypted and when your application
calls
the your
application calls the server to verify
it so server knows already the key how
to decrypt it so they will decrypt the
payload and then do
it f the information and check expiry
time and all and then do the
validation okay so third the interview
question comes is that
in the JWT token ultimately let's say
now you will get more clarity JWT and
jws JWT token if it is not jws in the
JWT token you have header you have
payload and there is no signature so in
the header you know that ALG part which
say that what algorithm you are using
for
Signature it is
none I am not signing
it so such that is known as unsecured
JWT where your algorithm is none for the
signature that JWT should be
rejected ultimately this is JWT there is
no signature part and algorithm is
none but this is known as unsecured JWT
jws is Json WAP signature where you have
a
algorithm RSA hm whichever and you have
doing the signature also putting the
signature but that is known as JW s but
since nobody is using JWT without the
signature so that's why the terms are
JWT jws used interchangeably because
nobody use JWT token with algo none
signature always
present okay so without signature it is
known as unsecured JWT which is never
entertained it should never be it should
always be rejected with algo with none
remember
now see this fourth and fifth part is
very important from uh you can say that
interview and uh uh the majorly attacker
which use there is something called
jwk jwk
exploit so in the
header I told you about type I told you
about algo but there is something called
jwk
also right it is uh your key Json WAP
key
so public key is shared in
this public key is shared in this all
and it say that so you know that
signature you have a
message so message is sign using what
key private
key and this verify message is verified
through
public key now this message JWT you got
a message and it is already
signed right and now this user is trying
to call
a resource server and passing the
JWT now this resource server should not
have any logic to read the in the header
there would be some jwk it will pass the
public key also this n or E combinedly
form a public key right this is I think
your exponent part and this is your
modulus part so these both combined make
a public
key so resource server should not
verify your JWT with the public key
which is coming inside this jwk no it
might be possible that attacker has
changed the message
right and put its own public key and it
changed the signature also the signature
of the so it is possible that in the
payload in the payload attacker has
added some added some values and it
signed it again with its
attacker private
key now it you got the JWT from this now
you have to verify this sign digitally
signed that it it is coming uh it is a
valid or not is data is tampered or not
if you use this public key which is
coming in this jwk you might get yes it
is verified because attacker might have
added its public key hey verify with my
public key so you might get accepted
this payload that this is valid payload
but might attacker might added some
other details which is not
intended so JWT exploit is that never
use public key which is shared inside
this jwk within a
header so what to
do how so now let's say that resource
owner want a public key want a public
key to verify it how to do that or let's
say that resource owner is calling the
authentication server now authentication
server has to get the public key to sign
it how it know there is something called
K ID key ID I told you initially right
there is something in the header also
there is something called kid which you
can add it inside a jwk also at the top
also so this K ID is nothing but a key
ID right and this key ID
is used by your authentication server
there
is you whatever the authentication
server you are using right
they all maintain a well-known jwk Json
so they have their own uh you can say
that a link where they have list of
public key list of public key which can
be
used so these are you can say that the
wh listed publ key which authentication
server can use and since these are
public key everybody can know it right
there's nothing to hide it so that's why
they have generally this kind of we uh
link whatever the author authorization
server authentication server third party
you are using they might have their own
well-known JW k. Json this will contain
the list of public key and each one will
have a ID so this ID is present here so
how the public key now authorization
server knows that which public key I
need to use to verify this signature it
uses the K ID
look it into its wh listed public key
and choose when K ID okay this is the
public key this is the K ID this is
somewhere stored securely publicly and
it will use
that so now you know that these are the
white listed these are the wh listed
public keis which can be used right and
with the kid you can get
that with the kid you can uh use that
from the
list so you got it now if attacker you
can say that what if attacker adds its
own public key here right and pass that
K ID right then it's an issue then we
have to use a third party that's why we
always say that choose a third party
properly who is well known has taking
all the precautions right security
measures otherwise attacker may add its
own public key into its Whit listed
right somehow and then pass its own kid
in the header and your author resource
server uh or maybe you when you pass
authentication server use that K ID and
he said that yes this is present into my
white listed public a let's accept this
payload so you got it right the these
are some of the issues with the uh
JWT and this is actually what JWT
is I hope it's uh clear what problem it
solves what problem it has no there is
no Silver Bullet for any technology JWT
is highly used but it has certain gaps
but there are like if used
properly right then it's uh like very
very beneficial it makes life easier
authentication
part okay guys see you soon bye and